so to see what the programmer has to go
through let's look at the message
passing program
this is a relatively simple program what
it's trying to do is compute
a sum
of a relatively large array in parallel
on four cores
so this is the overall array size it has
1024 elements
this is the number of processors we have
in a message passing program
each of the processors will get one
quarter of the array they cannot access
each other's memory directly so each one
of them only allocates its part of the
array in its memory each of them will
have its own sum variable and then what
happens is each of them iterates over
its part of the array
adding those array elements to the sum
this of course assumes that the elements
of the large array have somehow been
distributed to all of the processors if
they haven't been distributed already
then
we need to also write code that will
actually send the elements of the array
so that each of them gets a quarter of
the array
once we have computed the sum we need to
compute the final sum
and to do that we have to communicate so
what we will do is we will have one of
the processors
act as the summing up agent and it will
for every other processor
receive
the sum sent by that processor and add
it to its sum and then print the final
overall sum
what do the rest of the processors do
well what they do is they send
to processor zero what they have
collected so far and that's all they do
so as you can see we need to explicitly
send and then receive things in order
for communication between processors to
happen and also we have to explicitly
control what gets into whose part of
memory
we need to explicitly also in the
program
figure out how to match the sends and
receives because if we send something
and it's not received it's going to be a
problem and also if we wait to receive
something and there is no cent for it
it's going to be a problem we get stuck
here
so we need to know how many
processes to wait for
we need to send exactly what's expected
at that time and so on
but once we do all of this correctly
it's very easy for the programmer to see
which parts of this program are going to
be expensive as far as communication is
concerned because these are all local
accesses so they're relatively fast and
these are the only places where we
actually communicate